Finding Aid for the Colonial Court Records Group, 1665-1787 SR.401
State Archives of North Carolina
Colonial Court Records Group
1665-1787
SR.401
401
35.400 35.400
Colonial Courts
State Archives of North Carolina
Arrangement
The Colonial Court Records are arranged into 11 series. The General Court and Supreme Court series have been further arranged into two subseries each. See the Arrangement Note for each series for more information.
Access Restrictions
This record group is open for research.
Biographical/Historical
Records relating to any of the higher courts in early North Carolina represented in the series CCR are extremely scarce until 1683 and are almost non-existent for several higher courts well after that date. Records of the General Court, the most important of these courts in terms of powers and amount of business transacted, do not begin to be abundant until 1694. It is therefore necessary in many instances to draw only tentative conclusions about the structure and work of the courts during the colony's early years.
The court system of colonial North Carolina began to function some time shortly after the grant of Carolina to the Lords Proprietors in 1663, and the first court to open in the colony probably was composed of the governor and Council, the governor's advisory body. Extant records do not reveal its name or functions, or the year of its organization, but evidence suggests either 1664 or 1665. The governor and Council apparently sat as the highest court of law in the colony until 1698, during most of this time bearing the name "General Court" and hearing civil and criminal cases in both an original and an appellate capacity. During the early decades of the proprietary period, which lasted from 1663 to 1729, courts held by the governor and Council included the General Court, Court of Chancery, Palatine's Court, Council of State, Court of Grand Council, and Grand Court--the latter two possibly being variant names for the General Court. Several of the courts had executive as well as judicial powers, and all of them had jurisdiction over the entire colony. Functions as well as terminology were far from being firmly set during this period, and likely the courts had overlapping responsibilities. At different times until the 1690s, the governor and proprietors'; deputies convened as the "Palatine's Court," which appears from sparse records to have sat as both a judicial and executive body. For a brief period in the late 1670s, the term "Council of State" was used for the governor and Council sitting to perform various functions relating to the administration of estates. In addition, from an early date courts apparently were held by governors and councilors individually, although nothing is known about them aside from a reference in an act of 1670 empowering them to try persons accused of illegally trading with Indians.
A court intermediate between these higher courts and the lower, or precinct courts existed during much of the 1680s and early 1690s. Termed the "County Court of Albemarle," it was a court of first instance, employed a jury, and seems to have assumed most of the original jurisdiction of the higher courts, with the governor and Council sitting mainly as a court of appeal. In 1694 the governor and Council again were sitting as a lawcourt and a court of equity. The former court employed a jury in actions brought in original jurisdiction, the latter did not, and each had both original and appellate jurisdiction. The lawcourt was termed the General Court, and the court of equity was styled Court of Chancery.
Until 1754 the General Court was the highest court of law in the colony and ceased to be composed of the governor and Council after 1697. Except for the chief justice, the governor and Council appointed the court's members. The position of chief justice was created by the Lords Proprietors in 1712, and the appointment was reserved to the proprietors, later to the crown. The other members of the bench were usually during the proprietary era styled "assistants", occasionally "associates," and had to have the chief justice present in order to constitute a court. In the royal period down to 1746 they were called "assistants," and "associates;" thereafter--the latter term implying a role less subordinate to the chief justice than did the former.
The General Court had original jurisdiction over civil actions of a more consequential nature, as determined by the value of the matter at issue, and over crimes such as murder and counterfeiting, punishable by loss of life or member. The General Court also functioned as a court of appeals from judgments of precinct ("county" after 1739) courts, which had original jurisdiction over lesser civil actions and crimes. During the proprietary era the size of the bench varied from three to nine justices, with six or seven being the usual number. The bench enlarged when the court convened as a court of "oyer and terminer and general gaol [jail] delivery" for trying criminal actions, when it added to its number the Council and principal officials of the colony. After royalization, the number of assistant justices was four, and for a time there was a similar addition to its membership when it sat to try criminal cases.
The General Court normally convened three times a year to deal with both civil and criminal cases during the proprietary era, and three times a year for civil and twice for criminal proceedings during the royal period. A provost marshal served as executive officer of the General Court, summoning juries, serving writs, enforcing judgments, and the like. The clerk of the court kept the records, prepared the documents necessary for causes to be initiated and completed, and took minutes of the proceedings. An attorney general prosecuted criminal actions and brought civil suits on behalf of the Lords Proprietors and the crown. Grand juries brought indictments in criminal cases and petit juries determined facts in both criminal and civil actions. Attorneys pleading in the General Court had to be licensed by the governor. Litigations and prosecutions in the General Court generally followed English practice in form of action, principles of adjudication, and courtroom procedure. The court also employed in its deliberations the statute law of the colony, and to a lesser extent that of the mother country as well. The court shared with the lower courts such administrative functions as probate of wills, deeds, and landrights; appointment of guardians for orphans; and the like. With few exceptions, the courts in North Carolina were free of interference from authorities in London. Judgments in civil actions could, if of sufficient importance, be appealed to the Privy Council, and the crown could disallow legislation relating to the operation of courts, as it did on several occasions.
A major change in the General Court system came with the creation of circuits. The court had sat mainly in Perquimans County until 1716, when the town later incorporated as Edenton became its home. Three circuits (Bath, New Bern, and Wilmington), sitting twice a year, were created by the General Assembly in 1738. Civil actions were commenced and pleaded in the court in Edenton, and tried in the circuit courts. In 1746 the court's central office moved to New Bern, Edenton was added to the circuit, and Edgecombe Courthouse replaced Bath. Other changes, mostly minor, occurred from time to time. The term "provost marshal," for example, gave way to "sheriff,"and the offices of chief justice and attorney general were crown appointments after 1729. In broad outline, however, the court's organization, functions, and procedures remained much the same from 1698 until the General Court system came to an end in 1754.
In 1754 the General Court was abolished by statute and in its place five independent district courts were erected, seated in Edenton, Wilmington, Enfield, Salisbury, and New Bern. These courts, sitting twice yearly and termed the Supreme Courts of Justice, Oyer and Terminer and General Gaol Delivery, existed from 1755 through 1759. The chief justice and three other justices composed the bench of each court. The Supreme Courts were by act of assembly replaced in 1760 by District Superior Courts. These latter were essentially identical to the Supreme Courts, with the same jurisdiction and being seated in Edenton, Wilmington, Halifax, New Bern, and Salisbury, and from 1768, Hillsborough. The Superior Court system collapsed in 1772, when the royal government refused to permit a new court act to be passed replacing the one having recently expired, and superior courts were not revived until 1778.
The governor and Council sat as a Court of Chancery throughout the colonial period. The court adjudicated according to principles of equity, a relief that might be sought by a litigant when justice could not be obtained according to the principles of law. The volume of litigation handled by the court was much less than that of the General Court and its successors, although it exercised both original and at times appellate jurisdiction in noncriminal actions. Another court composed of the governor and Council was the Court of Claims, erected during the royal era to grant land and adjudicate disputes relating to land. A higher court undertaking little if any activity was the Court of Exchequer. Theoretically organized in the early 1730s to deal with questions relating to crown revenue, the court apparently sat no more than a few times. A Court of Vice Admiralty was constituted in the province in the late 1690s. The court dealt with maritime matters of all kinds, including mercantile and other noncriminal litigation, as well as crimes and the taking of prizes in wartime. The Court of Vice Admiralty dispensed justice according to principles of civil law, based on Roman codes rather than the precepts of the common law. The single judge, appointed by the governor and Council (as were the court's other officials), sat without a jury, and his judgments could be appealed to the High Court of Admiralty in London. Relatively few actions are known to have come before the Court of Vice Admiralty.
The authority by which proprietary higher courts were established in North Carolina was based on the royal charters granting Carolina to the Lords Proprietors. The proprietors then, through their series of Fundamental Constitutions devised from 1669 to 1698, attempted to determine the form and function of such courts. However, the cumbersome scheme set forth in the constitutions, with each of the eight proprietors'; deputies maintaining his own court, proved unworkable except for the partial implementation of the Palatine's Court. Much more important in determining the nature of the court system were the proprietors'; commissions and instructions to successive governors, which often included orders to establish, with the consent of the Council, such courts as they thought necessary. In a few instances the proprietors specified rules of procedure to be followed in the conduct of trials, but this was rare. Usually such details were left to be worked out in the province, as were the type and number of courts.
Little changed with the implementation of royal government. By the governor's commission, he and the Council were empowered to erect "such and so many Courts of Judicature and Public Justice" as they saw fit, and to appoint judges and other court officials. And with the exception of a small number of directives from the crown concerning such fundamental considerations as speedy trials, appeals, appointment and removal of judges, and habeas corpus, procedural matters were not addressed by the authorities in London.
A series of provincial statutes enacted during both the proprietary and royal periods prescribed much of the jurisdiction and procedure in the lawcourts. (Very little such legislation related to the Court of Chancery, and the Court of Exchequer and Court of Vice Admiralty operated entirely outside the purview of colonial laws.) A number of such acts related to specific procedural points, such as the act "concerning Appeals and Writs of Error" of 1715, and the act "directing the Method of appointing Jurymen" of 1762. Other acts in 1738, 1746, 1754, 1760, 1762, 1767, and 1773 (several of which were disallowed by the Privy Council in London), went much further, erecting courts, setting their jurisdiction, and prescribing their procedure in detail.
REFERENCES:
P.L., 1715, c. 22.
P.L., 1738, c. 6.
P.L., 1746, 2d sess., c. 2.
P.L., 1754, 2d sess., c. 1.
P.L., 1760, 2d sess., c. 1.
P.L., 1762, c. 1.
P.L., 1767, c. 1.
P.L., 1773, c. 1.
Fundamental Constitutions of Carolina, 1669-1698.
Parker, Mattie Erma Edwards, William S. Price, Jr., and Robert J. Cain, eds. NORTH CAROLINA HIGHER-COURT RECORDS. Vols. 2-6 of THE COLONIAL RECORDS OF NORTH CAROLINA (SECOND SERIES). Raleigh: Division of Archives and History, Department of Cultural Resources, 1968-1980.
Saunders, William S., ed. THE COLONIAL RECORDS OF NORTH CAROLINA. 10 vols. Raleigh: State of North Carolina, 1886-1890.
Provenance
The first set of Colonial Court Records to have been accessioned to the archives appear to have been the General Court Minutes and Perquimans Court Minutes,* which were acquired between 1914 and 1916. The legacy finding aid of the Colonial Court Records cited The Sixth Biennial Report of the North Carolina Historical Commission, December 1, 1914, to November 30, 1916 (p. 14-15) as its source when it stated that Miscellaneous Court Papers, 1693-1778, were brought to Raleigh from Chowan County, and that Court Records, 1688-1793, were brought from Perquimans County sometime during this biennial. Over the next several years after the records had been acquired, the court minutes were mounted into several volumes.
In 1961-62, court dockets and jury lists were received from the Chowan County Courthouse by the Clerk of the Superior Court in Edenton. These may or may not have come as bound volumes.
In 1963, General Court materials totaling approximately 45 fiberdex boxes of loose papers were brought to the Archives from the Chowan County Courthouse by the Clerk of the Superior Court in Edenton. It is noted in the legacy finding aid to the Colonial Court Records that some my have come from Perquimans County.
*Minutes of the Perquimans Precinct Court are found in Perquimans County Records and in Colonial Court Records.
District Superior Courts from the District Superior Courts,(recordgrp 100398)
Scope and Content
The Colonial Court Records contain information regarding the court records of North Carolina during the colonial period (late 1600s through the 1700s) when the colony was controlled by the proprietors and later the crown. Researchers will find materials that would have passed through the court system or is related to court proceedings including civil and criminal cases from the General Court and later the Supreme Court, and other various court documents such as administrative materials including appointments, oaths, commissions, and other non-criminal court proceedings. Cases from the Admiralty Court, Court of Chancery, General Court of Oyer and Terminer and General Gaol Delivery, Supreme Court, Court of Assize and Palatine Court, estate and land records, wills, court minutes and dockets, tax and account information and various correspondence and receipts are also part of this collection. There are additionally papers regarding specific subjects such as slaves and slavery, indenture servitude, apprentice papers and Native Americans, documents relating to maritime activity, infrastructure construction and repair, marriages and custody, and business and trade. There are 45 bound books and pamphlets of court minutes and dockets for the General Court, General Court of Oyer and Terminer, and Gaol Delivery, Vice Admiralty court, Court of Assize, and Supreme Court. The bulk dates of this collection are from 1720 to 1746, and the inclusive dates are from 1665 to 1787.
Courts; Justice, Administration of; Colonial Courts
- Court Minutes and Dockets, 1680-1770; SR.401.1; 401.1; CCR 115 - CCR 138; CCR 146 - CCR 147; CCR 189; Dockets Minutes; 10.200; Colonial Courts; Court of Assize; General Court; Supreme Courts of Justice (Box Minutes and Dockets (unbound), 1680-1764, Item General Court Papers, Minutes, 1693-1695, Item General Court Minutes, 1695-1703, Item General Court Papers, 1703, 1704, 1712-1714, Chowan, 1716-1729, Item General Court Minutes, 1705-1712, Item General Court Papers, Minutes, 1716-1724, Part I, 1716-1722, Item General Court Papers, Minutes, 1716-1722, Part II, 1722-1724, Item General Court Papers,Minute Docket, 1724-1730, Oct-Mar, Part I, 1724-1727, Oct-Mar., Item General Court Papers, Minute Docket, 1724-1730, Oct-Mar, Part II, 1727-1730, Jul-Mar., Item General Court Papers, Minutes, 1725, 1727, 1730, 1731-1732, 1732, 1733, 1736, 1745-1751, Part I, Item General Court Papers, Minutes, 1745-1751, Part II, Item General Court Papers, Minutes, 1750-1767, Part I, Item General Court Papers, Minutes, 1750-1767, Part II, Item Supreme Courts, Minute Docket, Oct. 1755-Oct. 1756, Item Supreme Courts, Minute Docket, Apr. 1757, Oct. 1759, Item General Court, Reference Docket, Mar. 1704, Jul. 1724-Mar. 1732 (Partial), Item General Court, Docquet, Oct. 1728-July 1738 (Partial), Item General Court Papers, Dockets, 1723, 1736, 1737, 1739, 1744, Item General Court, Sessions Docquet, 1734-1736, Item General Court, Docquet, Jul.-Oct. 1739, Item General Court, Docquet, Mar, Jul, Oct. 1740, Item General Court, Reference Docquet, Jul. 1741-Oct. 1742 (Partial), Item General Court, Docquet, Mar, Jul, Oct. 1741, Item General Court, Docquet, Mar, Jul, Oct. 1742, Item General Court, Docquet, Mar, Jul, Oct. 1743, Item General Court, Docquet, Mar-Jul. 1744, Item General Court Papers, Dockets, 1737, 1745-1746, Part I, Item General Court Papers, Dockets, 1745-1746, Part II, Item General Court Papers, Dockets, 1746-1747, Part I, Item General Court Papers, Dockets, 1746-1747, Part II, Item General Court Papers, Dockets, 1748-1752, Part I, Item General Court Papers, Dockets, 1748-1752, Part II, Item General Court Papers, Dockets, 1752-1753, Item General Court Papers, Dockets, 1754-1755, Part I, Item General Court Papers, Dockets, 1754-1755, Part II, 1770, Item General Court Papers, Dockets, 1752-1762, Part I, Item General Court Papers, Dockets, 1752-1762, Part II, Item Supreme Courts, Civil Trial Docket, April 1755-October 1755, Item Supreme Courts, Civil Trial Docket, Apr. 1756-Mar. 1760, Item General Court Papers, Vol. I, 1690-1716, Item General Court Papers, Vol. II, 1717-1754, n.d., Item Court Papers, District of Edenton, 1751-1787, Item Vice-Admiralty Papers, Vol I, 1697-1738, Item Vice-Admiralty Papers, Vol II, 1739-1746, Item Vice-Admiralty Papers, Vol III, 1746-1753, Item Vice-Admiralty Papers, Vol IV, 1754-1759, n.d., Box Court Minutes and Dockets (bound), 1693-1787)
  Arrangement
  Volumes are arranged by date and Court.
  Unbound materials are arranged by date and/or court.
  Scope and Content
  This series contains bound volumes and pamphlets as well as 2 boxes of unbound materials. Bound volumes and pamphlets include court minutes and dockets of the General Court, Perquimans Precinct Court, General Court of Oyer and Terminer & Gaol Delivery, General Sessions, Court of Chancery, Supreme Court, Superior Court of Pleas and Grand Sessions, Court of Exchequer, Court of Assizes and Vice Admiralty. Also included are commissions, lists of deeds, references, council minutes, and various jury lists. Counties in which the courts took place include, but not limited to, are Craven, Carteret, Johnston, Beaufort, Hyde, Chowan, Pasquotank, Perquimans, Currituck, Bertie, Tyrrell, Shaftsbury, Albemarle, District of New Bern, and District of Edenton. Some documents are fragments and unidentifiable.
  The unbound documents contain court minutes and dockets of the General Court, Oyer and Terminer, Goal Delivery, Vice Admiralty, Court of Assize, and Court of Chancery and General Court of Sessions. Also included are minutes of the council, and minutes of commissioners to examine the public treasury. There is additionally a crown docket from the Supreme Court which is bound. Dockets include docket references and attachments, writs, and references continuances dockets.
  - General Court Papers, Minutes, 1693-1695; CCR 101; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Minutes, 1695-1703; CCR 102; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers,1703, 1704, 1712-1714, Chowan, 1716-1729, 1703, 1704, 1712-1714, 1716-1729; CCR 103; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Minutes, 1705-1712; CCR 104; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Minutes, Part I, 1716-1724, 1716-1722; CCR 105; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Minutes, Part II, 1716-1722, 1722-1724; CCR 106; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Minute Docket, 1724-1730, Oct-Mar, Part I, 1724-1727, Oct-Mar., 1724-1730, 1724-1727; CCR 107; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Minute Docket,1724-1730, Oct-Mar, Part II, 1727-1730, Jul-Mar., 1724-1730, 1727-1730; CCR 108; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Minutes, Part I, 1725, 1727, 1730, 1731-1732, 1732, 1733, 1736, 1745-1751; CCR 109; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Minutes, Part II, 1745-1751; CCR 110; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Minutes, Part I, 1750-1767; CCR 111; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Minutes, Part II, 1750-1767; CCR 112; Colonial Courts
  - Supreme Courts, Minute Docket, Oct. 1755- Oct. 1756, 1755-1756; CCR 113; Colonial Courts
  - Supreme Courts, Minute Docket, Apr. 1757, Oct. 1759, 1757, 1759; CCR 114; Colonial Courts
  - General Court, Reference Docket, Mar. 1704, Jul. 1724- Mar. 1732 (Partial), 1704, 1724-1732; CCR 115; Colonial Courts
  - General Court, Docquet, Oct 1728- July 1738 (Partial), 1728-1738; CCR 116; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Dockets, 1723, 1736, 1737, 1739, 1744; CCR 117; Colonial Courts
  - General Court, Sessions Docquet, 1734-1736; CCR 118; Colonial Courts
  - General Court, Docquet, Jul-Oct., 1739; CCR 119; Colonial Courts
  - General Court, Docquet, Mar, Jul, Oct., 1740; CCR 120; Colonial Courts
  - General Court, Reference Docquet, Jul. 1741- Oct.1742 (Partial), 1741-1742; CCR 121; Colonial Courts
  - General Court, Docquet, Mar, Jul, Oct., 1741; CCR 122; Colonial Courts
  - General Court, Docquet, Mar, Jul, Oct., 1742; CCR 123; Colonial Courts
  - General Court, Docquet, Mar, Jul, Oct., 1743; CCR 124; Colonial Courts
  - General Court, Docquet, Mar.-Jul., 1744; CCR 125; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Dockets, Part I, 1737, 1745-1746; CCR 126; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Dockets, Part II, 1745-1746; CCR 127; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Dockets, Part I, 1746-1747; CCR 128; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Dockets, Part II, 1746-1747; CCR 129; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Dockets, Part I, 1748-1752; CCR 130; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Dockets, Part II, 1748-1752; CCR 131; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Dockets, 1752-1753; CCR 132; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Dockets, Part I, 1754-1755; CCR 133; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Dockets, Part, II, 1754-1755, 1770; CCR 134; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Dockets, Part I, 1752-1762; CCR 135; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Dockets, Part II, 1752-1762; CCR 136; Colonial Courts
  - Supreme Courts, Civil Trial Docket, April- October, 1755; CCR 137; Colonial Courts
  - Supreme Courts, Civil Trial Docket, Apr. 1756- Mar. 1760, 1756-1760; CCR 138; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Vol. I, 1690-1716; CCR 139; Colonial Courts
  - General Court Papers, Vol. II, 1717-1754, n.d.; CCR 140; Colonial Courts
  - Court Papers, District of Edenton, 1751-1787; CCR 141; Colonial Courts